Finding aid for League of Women Voters of Northwest Wayne County Records, 1957-2013 2014137 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library
League of Women Voters of Northwest Wayne County records
1957-2013
1973-1992
Bentley Historical Library
League of Women Voters of Northwest Wayne County.
2014137 Aa 2
3 linear feet
Records of the League of Women Voters (LWV) of Northwest Wayne County in Michigan and its predecessor organizations, the LWV of Livonia and the LWV of Northville-Plymouth-Canton-Novi. Collection includes organizational records, newsletters, correspondence, and other records documenting the activities of the three groups.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The record group was donated by the League of Women Voters of Northwest Wayne County (donor no. 11100 ) in May 2014.
Accruals
No further additions to the records are expected.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to research.
Biographical / Historical
The League of Women Voters (LWV) is a nonpartisan political organization that strives to increase active and knowledgeable participation by voters in the electoral process, educates citizens about critical public policy issues, and shapes these policies through its advocacy and educational programs. The LWV of Livonia, Mich. began with thirty-five members in 1960 and aimed to encourage active participation of local voters in the democratic process. In 2001, the branch was renamed the League of Women Voters of Northwest Wayne County; by 2014, its scope encompassed Livonia, Plymouth, Canton, Redford, Wayne, Garden City, Westland, and Northville Township. As of 2010, the Northwest Wayne County League had fifty volunteer members, both male and female. Members are also part of the League of Women Voters of Michigan (LWVMI) and the national League of Women Voters, both founded in 1920.
Northwest Wayne County's branch educates individuals to devise positive solutions to public policy problems and emphasizes conflict management. The organization maintains a nonpartisan stance, providing information on candidates but never endorsing or opposing any politician or political party. The League publishes free voter guides and "They Represent You," a pamphlet furnishing contact information for local, state, and federal government representatives. Interested voters may also attend candidate forums and educational meetings about ballot proposals and public policy concerns of interest to northwest Wayne County. The group frequently undertakes intensive studies of policy issues ranging from waste disposal to education to prison reform, making a recommendation only after members reach consensus. Furthermore, with money from dues, donations, and fundraisers, the branch funds scholarships for local students.
Members of the Northwest Wayne County group have received awards from the University of Michigan-Dearborn and other organizations for their community service and others have gone on to serve as LWVMI officers.
Arrangement
The records are divided into three series based on content and type: Issues, Organizational Records, and Voter Newsletter.
Scope and Contents
The records of the League of Women Voters (LWV) of Northwest County include organizational documents and publications, correspondence, membership rosters, local studies, and extensive meeting minutes drawn from all predecessor organizations but primarily from the LWV of Livonia. Although the documents encompass the years from 1957 to 2013, most are from the 1970s, 1980s, and 1990s. Researchers will find records of LWV operations, such as fundraising and board elections, as well as a wealth of information relating to urban challenges, social issues, and environmental concerns of the greater Detroit area in the late 20th century. A glimpse into broader state issues, such as Michigan's penitential system, also emerges in the documents. Extensive collections of LWV newsletters from the Livonia and Northville-Plymouth-Canton-Novi branches, as well as the subsequent merged organization, will also be of interest to those researching the political participation of women during and after the women's liberation movement.
Related Materials
Researchers may also wish to consult the following collections:
League of Women Voters of Allen Park, records
League of Women Voters of Berrien and Cass Counties, records
League of Women Voters of Dearborn-Dearborn Heights (Mich.), records
League of Women Voters of Grosse Pointe, records
League of Women Voters of Michigan, records
League of Women Voters of Monroe (Mich.), records
League of Women Voters of Mount Clemens-Clinton Area, records
League of Women Voters of the Ann Arbor Area, records
Environmental protection -- Michigan -- Wayne County.; Intergovernmental relations in the United States -- Michigan.; Wayne County (Mich.) -- Politics and government.; Women -- Michigan -- Wayne County.; Women -- Political activity -- Michigan -- Wayne County.; Videotapes.; League of Women Voters of Northwest Wayne County.
- Issues
  - Environmental Issues
    Scope and Contents
    The Issues series comprises documents relating to public policy concerns in which the LWV of Livonia was involved, primarily in the 1970s and 1980s. Researchers seeking to understand environmental issues during this period will find materials concerning solid waste disposal and the Lake Erie basin of particular interest. The series also encompasses a variety of social concerns, including Michigan prisons, urban planning into the 21st century, and Livonia-area public schools. Finally, the series addresses Wayne County and Michigan state politics as a whole, including the county charter, a proposed state constitutional convention in 1976-1977, and intergovernmental relations in the early 1990s. Some materials from the LWV of Northwest Wayne County are also included.
    - Waste Water Handbook, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Department of Natural Resources Solid Waste Management Act 641 Rules, 1982 (Box 1)
    - GEM Project (Livonia/Northville-Plymouth-Canton-Novi branches), 1990 (Box 1)
    - Diversions and Inter-Basin Transfers Position, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Lake Erie Basin Committee Notes, 1979-1990 (Box 3)
    - Livonia Recycling Millage Proposal, 1998 (Box 3)
    - "Demand and Supply: The Management and Marketing of Solid Waste, May 24, 1990", VHS videocassette (Box 3)
  - Educational Issues
    - Study of Livonia Public Schools, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Livonia Public Schools, Bentley High School, 1977-1985 (Box 1)
  - Urban Life Issues
    - Consensus: Cable TV, circa 1980 (Box 1)
    - "This is Livonia," 1962, 1976 and "Livonia 2000" 1986, 1962-1986 (Box 1)
    - League of Women Voters of the Detroit Metropolitan Area Policies and Files, 1973-1991 (Box 1)
      General
      includes minutes from February 6, 1991 meeting and discussion of Equal Housing Opportunity logo
    - Metropolitan Area Problems, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Other Social Issues
    - Consensus: Problems of the Retired, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Social Services: Livonia, circa 1980 (Box 1)
    - Wayne County Department of Social Welfare Budget Allowance, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Prisons Study, 1986-1990 (Box 3)
  - Wayne County Politics
    - Livonia Women's Commission, circa 1969 (Box 1)
    - League of Women Voters Guide to Wayne County Government, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Wayne County Home Rule, 1965; 1980; 1986 (Box 1)
    - Livonia Charter Amendment: Mayor, Clerk, and Treasurer, 1987 (Box 3)
  - State and National Politics
    - They Represent You, 2007-2008; 2011-2013 (Box 1)
    - "Tell It to Washington" Citizen Action Guide, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - League of Women Voters to Michigan Constitutional Convention, 1976-1977 (Box 3)
    - Intergovernmental Relations Position and Report on 2500 Michigan Governments, 1979; 1990 (Box 3)
- Organizational Records
  The Organizational Records series includes materials addressing the operations of the LWV of Livonia, the LWV of Northville-Plymouth-Canton-Novi, and the LWV of Northwest Wayne County. Correspondence, primarily from the Livonia presidency of Flora McRae (later president of the LWVMI), and meeting minutes constitute a substantial part of the series. Annual reports from the Livonia branch and its successor help to situate the organization's developments on a timeline. Committee notes and event-planning discussions also yield insight into the League's major activities, especially in the 1970s and 1980s. Membership lists provide a glimpse of the composition of the group.
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1971-1991 (Box 1)
      primarily from the presidency of Flora McRae
    - Livonia Logo Correspondence, 1985; 1987 (Box 3)
  - Meeting Minutes and Annual Reports
    - Board Minutes (Livonia), 1960 (Box 1)
    - Meeting Minutes of Plymouth-Canton-Northville League, October 1992-June 30, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Livonia Executive Board Meeting Minutes and Annual Reports
      - March 1985-April 1995 (Box 1)
      - September 1961-April 1984 (Box 1)
    - Annual Meeting Reports, 1980-2013 (Box 2)
    - Annual Meeting Reports, 1960-1980 (Box 2)
    - Livonia Annual Meeting Minutes, March 1961-May 1990 (Box 2)
    - Nominating Committee Notes, 1965-1986 (Box 3)
  - League Policies and Structure
    - Treasurer, Budgets, Budget Planning, 1957; 1987-1991 (Box 1)
    - State Policies, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Observer Program Manual, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Board Nonpartisan Policy, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Membership Rosters, 1991-2001 (Box 1)
    - Local By-Laws, 1973-1988 (Box 1)
    - Public Relations Information from State League, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Circulating Petitions, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Board Organization, 1985 (Box 1)
    - "Dollars and Sense: The Art of Fundraising," circa, 1975 (Box 1)
  - League Programs and Events
    - Information on Consultants, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Candidate Forum Outline, undated (Box 1)
    - Book Sale, 1988-1991 (Box 1)
    - LWVMI: "How to Do a Local Study," circa, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Program Planning, circa, 1990 (Box 1)
    - LWV of Livonia Local Studies, circa, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Voter Service, 1973; 1987 (Box 1)
    - Education Fund, 1990 (Box 3)
- Voter Newsletter
  The Voter Newsletter series contains locally-produced copies of the Voter, a newsletter published by each branch of the LWV. The newsletter covers the period from January 1978 to May 2001 for the Livonia group, October 1985 to May 1993 (with some gaps) for the Northville-Plymouth-Canton-Novi group, and July 2001 to December 2004 for the combined Northwest Wayne County group. Taken collectively, the publications provide comprehensive yet concise insight into the activities of the various branches.
  - Livonia Branch
    - June 1960-December 1963 (Box 2)
    - January 1964-April 1968 (Box 2)
    - April 1969-December 1973 (Box 2)
    - January 1974-December 1977 (Box 2)
    - March 1985-May 1992 (Box 2)
    - January 1978-December 1980 (Box 3)
    - January 1981-May 1991 (Box 3)
    - December 1995-May 2001 (Box 3)
  - Northville-Plymouth-Canton-Novi Branch
    - October 1985-December 1989 (Box 3)
    - March 1990-May 1993 (Box 3)
  - Northwest Wayne County Branch, July 2001-December 2004 (Box 3)